Guide to the Wendel White photographs, 2009-2019 RL.11065
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Wendel White photographs
2009-2019
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
White, Wendel A., 1956-
Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University)
RL.11065
4.0 Linear Feet 4 boxes 75 photographic prints 24x30 and 24x42 inches
Wendel White is a photographer and Distinguished Professor of Art at Stockton University in New Jersey. This photograph collection comprises two bodies of work by White that explore aspects of African American history through artifacts, archives, and 21st century landscapes. The first, "Manifest," comprises 45 24x30 inch color inkjet photographs of single objects relating to African American material culture and history, taken by White in various public and private collections throughout the U.S. Subjects in these stark images include a diary, printed notices, slavery narratives, a lock of Frederick Douglass's hair, a drum, a slave collar, a tobacco pouch, a tintype photograph, and other objects. "Manifest" is the 2015 winner of the Archive of Documentary Arts Collection Award for Documentarians of Color. The second portfolio, "Red Summer," refers to race-related violence against African Americans that took place from 1912 to 1923, with the majority occurring during the summer of 1919. It consists of 30 24x42 inch color photographs, taken by White from 2017 to 2018, at sites across the United States where violence against African Americans - assaults, riots, and lynchings - took place, paired with contemporaneous newspaper accounts of the events. Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
Arrangement
Photographic prints are arranged in original order as assigned by the artist.
Biographical Note
Wendel A. White was born in Newark, New Jersey, and grew up in New York, Pennsylvania, and New Jersey. He was awarded a BFA in photography from the School of Visual Arts in New York and an MFA in photography from the University of Texas at Austin. White is currently Distinguished Professor of Art at Stockton University in New Jersey.
He has received various awards and fellowships including a John Simon Guggenheim Foundation fellowship in photography, three artist fellowships from the New Jersey State Council for the Arts, a photography grant from the Graham Foundation for Advanced Studies in the Fine Arts, and a photography fellowship from En Foco Inc.
His work is represented in museum, library, corporate, and private collections. White's work is included in numerous publications including two books about his work, Manifest (published in 2014 by Chroma) and Small Towns, Black Lives (published in 2003 by the Noyes Museum of Art).
White has served on the board of directors for the Society for Photographic Education, the Atlantic City Historical Museum, New Jersey Black Culture and Heritage Foundation, and the New Jersey Council for the Humanities.
White's "Manifest" porfolio is the 2015 winner of the Archive of Documentary Arts Collection Award for Documentarians of Color. The ADA Collection Awards were established to diversify the ADA's collection in order to better reflect the multitude of viewpoints and communities from which work is being made in the documentary arts today.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Please exercise caution when using this collection as the digital color prints are easily abraded or scratched. Please refrain from touching the surface and do not flex the prints.
Provenance
The Wendel White Photographs were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 2015 and 2019.
Collection Overview
The Wendel White photographs collection consists of two bodies of work that explore aspects of African American history through images of artifacts, historical printed pieces and manuscripts, and 21st century landscapes.
The first, "Manifest," comprises 45 24x30 inch color inkjet photographs of single objects relating to African American material culture and history, taken by White in various public and private collections throughout the U.S. Subjects in these stark images include a diary, printed notices, slavery narratives, a lock of Frederick Douglass's hair, a drum, a slave collar, a tobacco pouch, a tintype photograph, and other objects. "Manifest" is the 2015 winner of the Archive of Documentary Arts Collection Award for Documentarians of Color.
The second portfolio, "Red Summer," refers to race-related violence against African Americans that took place from 1912 to 1923, with the majority occurring during the summer of 1919. It consists of 30 24x42 inch color photographs, taken from 2017 to 2018, of the sites across the United States where violence against African Americans - assaults, riots, lynchings - took place, paired with contemporaneous newspaper accounts of the events.
The photographer notes: "Several projects that have occupied my attention during the past two decades are, in retrospect, part of a broader effort to seek out the ghosts that continue to haunt the remnants of the past." The full artist's statements on "Manifest" and "Red Summer" are included in the series descriptions for those projects.
A photobook based on the "Manifest" project was published in 2014 by Chroma (California Institute of Integral Studies) as Manifest. Images from both projects have been exhibited in institutions across the U.S.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
The photographs in this collection were made with a 4x5 inch film-based camera. The prints were produced in 2015 and 2019 and are pigment-based inkjet on paper.
Banner
Due to their size and vulnerability, "Red Summer" prints are temporarily unavailable pending custom rehousing by Conservation staff.
African American families; African American photographers -- United States; African Americans -- Material culture; Documentary Photography -- United States; Lynching -- United States -- History; Photographers -- United States; Race riots; Slavery -- United States -- History; United States -- Race relations -- History; Color prints (photographs); Cultural artifacts.; Inkjet prints; Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University); Douglass, Frederick, 1818-1895
- Manifest, 2009-2019; 3.0 Linear Feet 2 boxes 45 photographic prints 24 x 30 inches; 22 x 27 1/2 inches
  Scope and Contents
  The 45 photographic prints in this series are from Wendel White's project titled "Manifest," initiated in 2009 and continuing into 2019. White included the following abstract about his work:
  "The Manifest portfolio images are photo-based representations of objects, documents, photographs, and books made in various public and private collections throughout the U.S. These repositories encompass elements of material culture such as diaries, slave collars, human hair, a drum, souvenirs, and other objects, some with great significance and others simply quotidian representations of daily life, from the history of the African American community.
  This project (Manifest) is an effort to seek out the cultural artifacts of the American concept and representation of race. The histories of slavery, abolition, segregation, the U.S. Civil War, and the Civil Rights Era are a few of the narratives that emerge in these photographs.
  I am increasingly interested in the residual power of the past to inhabit these material remains. The ability of objects to transcend lives, centuries, and millennia, suggests a remarkable mechanism for folding time, bringing the past and the present into a shared space that is uniquely suited to artistic exploration. While the artifacts are remarkable as visual evidence of lives and events, I also intend the viewer to consider this informal reliquary as a survey of the impulse and motivation to preserve history and memory.
  Several projects that have occupied my attention during the past two decades are, in retrospect, part of a broader effort to seek out the ghosts that continue to haunt the remnants of the past. I am drawn to the stories that dwell within these objects."
  "Manifest" received the 2015 Archive of Documentary Arts Award for Documentarians of Color. A recent book based on this work was published by Chroma (California Institute of Integral Studies) as Manifest and is available through the Chroma website.
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  The photographs were made with a 4x5" film-based camera. They were printed in 2015 and 2019, and are pigment-based inkjet on paper.
  - Hair, Frederick Douglass, Rush Rhees Library, University of Rochester, New York, 2009 (Box 1, Image RL.11065-P-0001)
  - First book purchased after slavery, Frederick Douglass, Rush Rhees Library, University of Rochester, New York, 2009 (Box 1, Image RL.11065-P-0002)
  - Zora Neale Hurston sketch book, Smathers Library Special Collections, University of Florida, Gainesville, 2012 (Box 1, Image RL.11065-P-0003)
  - Spoon, Harriet Tubman Home, Auburn, New York, 2009 (Box 1, Image RL.11065-P-0004)
  - Coin, Harriet Tubman Home, Auburn, New York, 2009 (Box 1, Image RL.11065-P-0005)
  - Rev. and Mrs. Loguen, Onondaga Historical Association, Syracuse, New York, 2009 (Box 1, Image RL.11065-P-0006)
  - Dr. Cliford Hancock Sr., Nebraska State Historical Society, Lincoln, Nebraska, 2011 (Box 1, Image RL.11065-P-0007)
  - Day is Dawn, Nebraska State Historical Society, Lincoln, Nebraska, 2011 (Box 1, Image RL.11065-P-0008)
  - FBI files, Malcolm X, Nebraska State Historical Society, Lincoln, Nebraska, 2011 (Box 1, Image RL.11065-P-0009)
  - Afro-American Sentinel, 1899. Great Plans Black History Museum, Omaha, Nebraska, 2011 (Box 1, Image RL.11065-P-0010)
  - Watch, Larkin Franklin Sr., Eatonville Historic Preservation, Eatonville, Florida, 2012 (Box 1, Image RL.11065-P-0011)
  - Tintype, Fenton History Center, Jamestown, New York, 2009 (Box 1, Image RL.11065-P-0012)
  - Sybil Flippin, glass plate negative, Stuhr Museum of the Prairie Pioneer, Grand Island, Nebraska, 2011 (Box 1, Image RL.11065-P-0013)
  - Eva Noles scrapbook, University Archives, State University of New York at Buffalo, 2009 (Box 1, Image RL.11065-P-0014)
  - Dr. Johnson journal, 1857, University Archives, State University of New York at Buffalo, 2009 (Box 1, Image RL.11065-P-0015)
  - Leather jump rope, Great Plains Black History Museum, Omaha, Nebraska, 2011 (Box 1, Image RL.11065-P-0016)
  - Will Brown lynching, Nebraska State Historical Society, Lincoln, Nebraska, 2011 (Box 1, Image RL.11065-P-0017)
  - Frederick Douglass hair, Nebraska State Historical Society, Lincoln, Nebraska, 2011 (Box 1, Image RL.11065-P-0018)
  - Buxton Association Picnic (Olin), State Historical Society of Iowa, Des Moines, Iowa, 2011 (Box 1, Image RL.11065-P-0019)
  - Graduation ring, Stuhr Museum of the Prairie Pioneer, Grand Island, Nebraska, 2011 (Box 1, Image RL.11065-P-0020)
  - Diary, Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library, Ithaca, New York, 2009 (Box 1, Image RL.11065-P-0021)
  - Lunch box, Larkin Franklin Sr., Eatonville Historic Preservation, Eatonville, Florida, 2012 (Box 1, Image RL.11065-P-0022)
  - Drum, Dan Desdunes Band, Great Plains Black History Museum, Omaha, Nebraska, 2011 (Box 1, Image RL.11065-P-0023)
  - Women's hood, New Jersey WKKK [Women of the Klu Klux Klan], Unidentified Southern New Jersey cultural organization, 2015 (Box 1, Image RL.11065-P-0024)
  - Hand drawn map of Eatonville, Olin Library Archives, Rollins College, Winter Park, Florida, 2012 (Box 1, Image RL.11065-P-0025)
  - Confederate shell, Fort Sumter 1861, Alexander Library Special Collections, Rutgers University, New Brunswick, New Jersey, 2014 (Box 1, Image RL.11065-P-0026)
  - Slave collar, Alexander Library Special Collections, Rutgers University, New Brunswick, New Jersey, 2014 (Box 1, Image RL.11065-P-0027)
  - Little Black Sambo, Paul W. Schopp, Riverton, New Jersey, 2014 (Box 1, Image RL.11065-P-0028)
  - Loan receipt, Smathers Library Special Collections, University of Florida, Gainesville, 2012 (Box 1, Image RL.11065-P-0029)
  - Decorative coin bank, Cape May County Museum, Cape May Courthouse, New Jersey, 2015 (Box 1, Image RL.11065-P-0030)
  - America's Greatest Problem: The Negro. Historical Library of the College of Physicians, Philadelphia, 2019; Original identifier: 1154 (Box 2, Image RL.11065-P-0031)
    Edition #1.
  - Bottle, Robeson House Collection, Arts Council of Princeton, New Jersey, 2017; Original identifier: 1142 (Box 2, Image RL.11065-P-0032)
  - Broken glass jar, Robeson House Collection, Arts Council of Princeton, New Jersey, 2017; Original identifier: 1141 (Box 2, Image RL.11065-P-0033)
    Edition #2.
  - Emancipation of slave woman and daughter, September 1815. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University, Durham, North Carolina, 2019; Original identifier: 1150 (Box 2, Image RL.11065-P-0034)
  - Intestine, male, African descent, 1849 cholera. Mütter Museum of the College of Physicians, Philadelphia, 2019; Original identifier: 1155 (Box 2, Image RL.11065-P-0035)
  - Key, Robeson House Collection, Arts Council of Princeton, New Jersey, 2017; Original identifier: 1146 (Box 2, Image RL.11065-P-0036)
  - Narrative of Sojourner Truth, 1850, Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, John Hope Franklin Center, Duke University, Durham, North Carolina, 2019; Original identifier: 1147 (Box 2, Image RL.11065-P-0037)
  - Natural History of Caucasian and Negro Races, Historical Library of the College of Physicians, Philadelphia, 2019; Original identifier: 1152 (Box 2, Image RL.11065-P-0038)
  - Pen, Robeson House Collection, Arts Council of Princeton, New Jersey, 2017; Original identifier: 1145 (Box 2, Image RL.11065-P-0039)
  - "Recruiting Colored Regiments" postcard, Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University, Durham, North Carolina, 2019; Original identifier: 1149 (Box 2, Image RL.11065-P-0040)
  - Richard Wharton slave trade contract, Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University, Durham, North Carolina, 2019; Original identifier: 1148 (Box 2, Image RL.11065-P-0041)
  - Sketches of Aborigines, Colonial New South Wales. Historical Library of the College of Physicians, Philadelphia, 2019; Original identifier: 1153 (Box 2, Image RL.11065-P-0042)
  - Skull inscribed 'Negro.' Mütter Museum of the College of Physicians, Philadelphia, 2019; Original identifier: 1156 (Box 2, Image RL.11065-P-0043)
  - Slave policy, Charter Oak Life Insurance, Hartford, Connecticut. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University, Durham, North Carolina, 2019; Original identifier: 1151 (Box 2, Image RL.11065-P-0044)
  - Tobacco pouch, Robeson House Collection, Arts Council of Princeton, New Jersey, 2017; Original identifier: 1143 (Box 2, Image RL.11065-P-0045)
- Red Summer, 2017-2018; 1.5 Linear Feet 1 box 30 photographic prints 24x42 inches
  Arrangement
  Prints are arranged in original order as received.
  The photographs in this collection were printed in 2019 on an Epson 7880, with Epson Legacy Etching paper and Epson Ultrachrome Pigment inks.
  Each of the 30 large prints in Wendel White's project "Red Summer" features a color photograph, taken from 2017 to 2018 with a 4x5" film camera, of a site in the United States where racially-motivated violence chiefly against African Americans took place; the image is paired with a color reproduction of a newspaper account of that event, sometimes in the same city, but often in a different area of the country. Most of the events took place in the so-called "Red Summer" of 1919. Practically all regions of the U.S. are represented, from California to Arizona, Nebraska to Texas, and Georgia to Delaware. The color inkjet prints measure 24x42 inches.
  The photographer includes this statement on his work:
  "The Red Summer portfolio represents the stories of various locations in the American landscape where racial violence (often characterized as 'Race Wars' at the time) erupted between 1917 and 1923. These years of conflict reveal several aspects of racial anxiety that inform our contemporary experience, including, though not limited to; racism, fear of violent black revolt, lynching, poverty, mass incarceration, and competition for employment.
  The project is a series of large format prints (currently available at 24" x 42") that combine photographs of the contemporary landscape made at or near the site of racial conflict with fragmented selections of contemporaneous newspaper reporting (1917-1923). In many cases the newsprint images include the surrounding stories or advertisements. The combination of the landscape photograph and the reproduction of newspaper fragments (which invade the contemporary with a narrative from the past), is a rupture and a conversation on the timeline between past and present.
  The conceptualization of 'the veil' as expressed by DuBois, has been a visual metaphor for the representation of race within my work for several decades; particularly in the two projects known as 'Schools for the Colored' and 'Red Summer.' The newspaper, a form of public record and commentary, is a veil of information through which most of the country as well as many in the international community, understood and misunderstood these events."
  - Bizbee, Arizona, July 3, 1919. The Washington Post, Washington, DC, July 5, 1919, 2017 (Box 3, Image RL.11065-P-0046)
    Original identifier: 1107
  - Bogalusa, Louisiana, November 22, 1919. The Watchman and Southron, Sumter, South Carolina, November 26, 1919, 2017 (Box 3, Image RL.11065-P-0047)
    Original identifier: 1130
  - Cadwell, Georgia, August 28, 1919. Chicago Tribune, Chicago, Illinois, August 29, 1919, 2017 (Box 3, Image RL.11065-P-0048)
    Original identifier: 1119
  - Charleston, South Carolina, May 10, 1919. The Morning News, Wilmington, Delaware, May 12, 1919, 2017 (Box 3, Image RL.11065-P-0049)
    Original identifier: 1120
  - Chicago, Illinois, July 27-August 3, 1919. The Fort Wayne News and Sentinel, Fort Wayne, Indiana, July 29, 1919, 2017 (Box 3, Image RL.11065-P-0050)
    Original identifier: 1105
  - Corbin, Kentucky, October 30, 1919. El Paso Herald, El Paso, Texas, October 31, 1919, 2017 (Box 3, Image RL.11065-P-0051)
    Original identifier: 1108
  - Donora, Pennsylvania, October 9, 1919. Bridgeport Times and Evening Farmer, Bridgeport, Connecticut, October 9, 1919, 2017 (Box 3, Image RL.11065-P-0052)
    Original identifier: 1109
  - Dublin, Georgia, July 15, 1919. The Emancipator, Montgomery, Alabama, July 19, 1919, 2017 (Box 3, Image RL.11065-P-0053)
    Original identifier: 1121
  - East St. Louis, Illinois, July 2, 1917. The Charlotte Observer, Charlotte, North Carolina, October 23, 1917, 2017 (Box 3, Image RL.11065-P-0054)
    Original identifier: 1106
  - East St. Louis, Illinois, July 2, 1917. The Daily Times, New Philadelphia, Ohio, July 3, 1917, 2017 (Box 3, Image RL.11065-P-0055)
    Original identifier: 1110
  - Elaine, Arkansas, October 1, 1919. Muskogee County Democrat, Muskogee, Oklahoma, October 2, 1919, 2017 (Box 3, Image RL.11065-P-0056)
    Original identifier: 1111
  - Fort Logan, Houston, Texas, August 23, 1917. The Kingston Daily Freeman, Kingston, New York, August 24, 1917, 2017 (Box 3, Image RL.11065-P-0057)
    Original identifier: 1112
  - Gary, Indiana, October 4, 1919. Evening Capital News, Boise, Idaho, October 6, 1919, 2017 (Box 3, Image RL.11065-P-0058)
    Original identifier: 1122
  - Hubbard, Ohio, October 10, 1919. The Sun, New York, New York, October 11, 1919, 2017 (Box 3, Image RL.11065-P-0059)
    Original identifier: 1135
  - Knoxville, Tennessee, August 30, 1919. Democrat and Chronicle, Rochester, New York, September. 1, 1919, 2017 (Box 3, Image RL.11065-P-0060)
    Original identifier: 1113
  - Longview, Texas, July 10, 1919. The Dallas Express, Dallas, Texas, July 19, 1919, 2017 (Box 4, Image RL.11065-P-0061)
    Original identifier: 1114
  - Milan, Georgia, May 25, 1919. The Greenville News, Greenville South Carolina, July 25, 1919, 2017 (Box 4, Image RL.11065-P-0062)
    Original identifier: 1123
  - Millen, Georgia, April 13, 1919. The New York Age, New York, New York, April 19, 1919, 2017 (Box 4, Image RL.11065-P-0063)
    Original identifier: 1125
  - Millen, Georgia, April 13, 1919. The New York Age, New York, New York, April 19, 1919, 2017 (Box 4, Image RL.11065-P-0064)
    Original identifier: 1126
  - Norfolk, Virginia, July 21, 1919. Carlisle Evening News, Carlisle, Pennsylvania, July 23, 1919, 2017 (Box 4, Image RL.11065-P-0065)
    Original identifier: 1127
  - Omaha, Nebraska, September 28, 1919. Arkansas Democrat, Little Rock, Arkansas, Sep 29, 1919, 2017 (Box 4, Image RL.11065-P-0066)
    Original identifier: 1133
  - Omaha, Nebraska, September 28, 1919. Iowa City Press-Citizen, Iowa City, Iowa, September 29, 1919, 2017 (Box 4, Image RL.11065-P-0067)
    Original identifier: 1115
  - Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, July 28-29, 1918. Evening Public Ledger, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, July 29, 1918, 2018 (Box 4, Image RL.11065-P-0068)
    Original identifier: 1137
  - Rosewood, Florida. January 1, 1923. The Palm Beach Post, West Palm Beach, Florida, January 8, 1923, 2017 (Box 4, Image RL.11065-P-0069)
    Original identifier: 1116
  - San Francisco, California, July 1, 1919. San Francisco Chronicle, San Francisco, California, July 1, 1919, 2017 (Box 4, Image RL.11065-P-0070)
    Original identifier: 1129
  - Tulsa, Oklahoma, May 31-June 1, 1921. The Arizona Republic, Phoenix, Arizona, June 2, 1921, 2017 (Box 4, Image RL.11065-P-0071)
    Original identifier: 1117
  - Tulsa, Oklahoma, May 31, 1919. The New York Age, New York, New York, June 4, 1921, 2017 (Box 4, Image RL.11065-P-0072)
    Original identifier: 1128
  - Washington, DC, July 21, 1919. Orlando Morning Sentinel, Orlando, Florida, July 23, 1919, 2018 (Box 4, Image RL.11065-P-0073)
    Original identifier: 1139
  - Washington, DC, July 21, 1919. The Washington Times, Washington, DC, July 22, 1919, 2018 (Box 4, Image RL.11065-P-0074)
    Original identifier: 1138
  - Youngstown, Ohio, July 25, 1917. The Tribune, Coshocton, Ohio, July 27, 1917, 2017 (Box 4, Image RL.11065-P-0075)
    Original identifier: 1118